# Jyoti Thakur



## Data Analyst

+91 - 9165182566

**<u>Value of the State of State**</u>

GitHub

### PROFILE SUMMARY

Dedicated professional with 3 years of hands-on data analysis using tools such as Power BI, DAX, SQL, Advanced Excel, Power Automate, and Python. Experienced in data cleaning, data modeling, analyzing, and designing reports and dashboard using Power BI Desktop and deployed in Power BI Service. Experienced in automating workflow and creating interactive Power BI Dashboards.

#### **KEY SKILLS AND TOOLS**

- Key Skills: DAX, Data Visualization, Data Modeling, Data Cleaning, Data Storytelling via Dashboard, Advanced MS Excel, Python, Statistical analysis
- Language: Python(Pandas, NumPy), Java, SQL
- Tools: Power BI, MS Excel, Power Automate, SSIS, SSAS, Jira, ServiceNow
- Database: Oracle, MySQL, MS SQL Server
- Other: Basic of Machine learning (Linear and Logistic Regression, Decision Trees), Problem solving, Agile Methodologies

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Power BI Developer | IBM (Cigna HealthCare Insurance Company)

[Jan 2023 –Present]

- Developed and maintained Power BI dashboards to track (KPIs) related to insurance sales, claims processing, customer retention and Forecasting also Conducted data cleaning and transformation using Power Query to prepare datasets for analysis.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to identify business requirements and develop data-driven solutions resulting save 20% of time for Dashboard making and participated in team meetings and contributed ideas for improving data visualization and reporting processes.
- Created a comprehensive Power BI dashboard to visualize insurance sales, policy performance by product, region, and sales channel.
- Initiated data integrity checks, reducing data errors and inconsistencies by 15%.
- Analyzed sales trends and identified opportunities for growth, resulting in a [25%] increase in sales revenue.
- Contributed to data modeling efforts to ensure data accuracy and consistency
- Used multiple time intelligence Function YTD, MTD, QTD etc.

## Power BI Data Analyst | IBM (Thames Water Utilities Ltd)

[May 2021 -Dec 2022]

- Adept in developing, publishing and scheduling power bi report as per requirements, Implemented Row Level Security and Conducted data analysis to identify trends, patterns, and anomalies in large datasets
- Utilized SQL for data extraction, transformation, and loading (ETL) processes.
- Presented findings and recommendations to stakeholders for informed decision-making resulting 10% growth in profit
- Developed complex DAX calculations and measures to derive insights from raw data
- Implemented dynamic filters, drill-down capabilities to enable users to explore data at granular levels that reduce the size of dashboard by 10%
- Played a key role in the maintenance of SQL databases using CTE and Temporary table that helped in reducing data retrieval time by 20%.

Data Analyst Sample Project Portfolio - <u>Jyoti Portfolio.com</u>

**Power Bi, SQL, Excel** projects can be found on my Portfolio Website.

#### **EDUCATION**

Master of Computer Application (MCA) SAM College Of Eng. And Technology, Bhopal, 2017 – 2019

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) | Guru Kripa College of Professional Studies, Bareli 2013-2016

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

- Microsoft Certified: Power BI Data Analyst Associate
- Microsoft Power BI Desktop for Business Intelligence by Udemy
- · Python for Data Science
- Data Science Foundation

## AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Champion Learner Gold Award 2022 & 2021 IBM
- Performance Award Bluepoint's and \$ Cash 2021 & 2023 |IBM
- IBM Growth Award 2022